Hello, and welcome back to part two of
electromagnetic radiation in chemistry.
So we're going to be continuing off
where we left off, which is looking at
quantum mechanics and how we are going
to define this idea of quantization in
terms of orbitals for especially the
first with the Bohr model and how it has
orbits and how it succeeds to an extent,
but does not quite explain the complete
picture of electron configuration.
Let's take a look.
Now, quantum is where
physics broke in the 1900s.
Since then, they've done a lot of
formulas to figure out a lot of the
details behind it, but there's still
a lot to be tried and understood.
So, it all kind of, it all goes with
where you look at a really small scale.
So, when you're trying to
describe how matter works, It
falls under two categories.
There's small and big.
Bigger scale is usually like more on
the scale of biology, believe it or not.
Smaller is when we talk about atomic,
meaning quantum for atomic, and usually
more thermo chemistry for the bigger
picture, which we'll learn about as well.
So when we're looking at that small
scale, this is where the idea of
the quan of the photon came about.
And being that we have this light matter
interaction, this is where the, the
term quantization will come in as well,
meaning that materials need to absorb
a very specific amount of energy in
order for them to be able to emit light.
They just don't happen out of nowhere.
It needs to be specific, right?
It's like trying to pay a very specific
amount to, uh, buy an item, right?
You can't just, you know,
go, you can't pay under.
You can pay over, but you're
gonna get change back, right?
You need to pay a specific
amount to buy something.
It's the same idea.
Now, when we give these, when we're seeing
photons at specific energy levels, this
is what allows you to be able to get a
specific fingerprint for all the different
pieces of matter that exist in the world.
If it's something that can emit a
photon, You can actually be able to
identify different species, whether
atomic, molecular, biological, um,
medical cancer, cancers, whatever tests,
if you can potentially apply these
concepts to them, and it's being done
even today in many different industries.
So in lab, what we're going to
be seeing is using different
lamps here to be able to observe
how different atoms will behave.
They all have completely different spectra
is what we call, what we'll be looking at.
So notice how each one of
them is a different color.
Mercury up top is blue.
Helium is like a pinkish color.
Hydrogen is red.
So they all have their own unique
pattern of, uh, emission lines that
we'll see based on how electrons are
behaving within all these species.
So exactly how does this kind of work?
Well, when you take in the light from one
of these lamps and you separate it, so
you're going to be kind of spying at all
these lamps and looking directly at them.
It's going to separate the light
into a prism and you'll actually see
these unique lines that are here.
which is like a fingerprint for each atom.
I'll give you that ability to be
able to see exactly what it is
that you are looking at in the lab.
Now, when we're trying to do this,
how exactly is this going to work?
Well, it is going to be, this is going to
be a little bit complicated to understand.
Bear with me.
Try to, so this model with excitation
and relaxation with the Bohr model
only truly works with hydrogen,
which is why it's going to be the
one you're going to do calculations
for using a Rydberg equation in lab.
We'll get to that then.
You try to understand exactly how
the excitation and relaxation works.
So, think of it this way, all,
every single electron, right, that
is here, has a circular orbit.
Now, if you remember, each of
those orbits were based on the
rows of the Pirog table, right?
So, each one had a new energy level.
This is what we're going to
refer to as a quantum number.
We're going to use the letter N
to determine that one orbital.
Okay, so with each of those, right,
you can see all the way in the
center is N is equal to 1, and as
it moves out, it goes N is equal to
2, N is equal to 3, and so forth.
So what is going to be happening
is electron orbits are quantized,
meaning that they have a very
specific amount of energy.
to access each orbital.
So one way to think about it is think
of an elevator that you're taking
to different floors of a building.
You hit a button for the second floor.
It takes so much energy for the elevator
to get pulled up to the second floor.
You can hit the third floor.
It takes so much energy to get
pulled to the third floor, to
the fourth floor and beyond.
And you can travel between floors as
well that require a certain amount of
energy from the motor to pull it up.
So the quantization is very similar to how
an elevator works up and down a building.
Now, with the N value, higher that
value is, so if it's N is equal to
1 versus, let's say, N is equal to
5, the bigger the number, the more
energy that it's going to have, and
the farther it is from the nucleus,
because it's going a farther distance.
So if I want to start at the first
floor and go all the way up to the fifth
floor, it's going to take a longer time
and more work in order to get there.
Now how does transitioning
between the orbitals work?
Well, the larger it is, the more
energy that it's going to need, right?
So first way that it can
happen is via excitation.
So it's like getting that
energy to go all the way up.
So if you want to look
at it like stairs, right?
To go up the stairs, if I want to go from
the first to the second floor, not so bad.
But if I want to go from the first
to the fifth floor, that's going
to take a lot of work in order
to get all the way up to the top.
So we excite things in order to
go from one level to the other.
Now when we come back
down, the goal is to relax.
So we can relax all the way back to the
bottom, and this is how electrons will
get excited to higher levels, and they
can relax back down to lower levels.
And the goal is always
to try to be relaxed.
So if they absorb a bunch of energy
and you're kind of running around
and you're really anxious and have
a ton of energy, either you need
to find a way to relax, right?
That's something that even humans
need to do on a normal basis, right?
We always need to find a way to relax.
So looking at this, how is it going
to look at in terms of a picture?
Now you don't have to be an
expert on knowing all this is kind
of have the basic idea, right?
So if I have, let's say a
hydrogen that's stuck in a lamp.
What we're going to do is
we're going to excite it.
How is that going to work?
You plug it into a wall, it's going
to put a lot of electricity into it.
It's going to essentially cause that
electricity to go in, and it's going to
move the electrons up into higher levels.
Now, when it does that, well, if I
excite it, let's say from 1 to 3, well,
it's going to have to relax back down.
Being that once notice how it's the
little red dot is in the third level.
Well, if it's going to
relax, how can I do that?
The only way I can, it's
by releasing a photon.
This is how it relax.
It needs to get rid of the energy.
How do you do it right?
There needs to be some kind
of method for you to relax.
For a lot of you, I can see that your
relaxation methods might be just be
playing video games, or maybe you have
a lot of hobbies on your own that help
you relax or something that you do.
In this case, it needs to relax, it's
going to release a red photon, and
that can be observed being it's energy
related at a specific wavelength.
So if you notice in the top, uh, left
corner of that spectrum all the way up
there, you get 656 nanometers is red.
So that's that transition, that relaxation
is what you're observing with your eye.
Now, you can see that specific
transition, and it's going to relate
to a very specific transition from n
equals 3 to n is equal to 2, and we
can observe that, and the way that kind
of works is depending on the distance,
these are referred to as energy gaps,
meaning in order for it to either go up
or go down, it needs to either absorb
a Get excited or essentially release
or relax a very specific amount of
energy, which we'll see via a photon.
So now the way to kind of picture this
This exact amount is, I like to use my
crappy drawings to show this, and it's
all about, let's say if I have a toll
road that I have to go through, right,
we don't have a lot of them here in
uh, central California, but if you need
to go through a toll, and you need to
spend a, and the only thing that they
do is they accept only exact change,
how can you go through that toll?
There's only so many
possibilities for you to do that.
So it's the same idea as your
lines that you're seeing.
Let's say if I want to go through the
5 toll, well, what's your option here?
If you only have a 5, a 10 bill, and
a 20 bill, what option do you have?
The only way for you to go
through is by paying a 5 bill.
So that is one photon of light is the 5.
If I want to go through the 20
toll, what options do you have?
Well, you could give the
20, you could give two tens.
Two or four fives, two fives and a ten,
you have options, meaning that there could
be multiple lines that are available to be
seen, right, in terms of the quantum side.
So when you have options, you can
see that there are going to be many
different lines that are possible.
So if you can see like helium has a
bunch of lines, barium has more lines.
And then white light is referring to kind
of staring at your fluorescence light.
It's a spectrum of many lines because
there's many elements in that.
Um, now every single one of these
things has a unique spectrum.
It's like a barcode at a grocery
store or a Target or wherever.
It goes to every single
individual item in the store.
Essentially every one of these is like a
barcode that has a very specific signature
for any of these individual elements.
So, when essentially this has that
light being emitted, we can exactly
see any of these types of things, which
is what we're going to be observing
in straightforward in lab, is all
these elements are unique, right?
They have unique properties, so going
back to the, they all have, they're
a unique piece of matter, they have
unique properties, and they have
unique spectrum that can be seen
firsthand, and you can see the atomic
signatures of atoms exist via using the
spectroscopy, and that's the cool part.
What's the summary here?
So the whole big thing is, the
first thing is that the Bohr model,
what does it suggest in the end?
The Bohr model is not going
to be our final model.
There's going to be one more that's going
to be way more complicated, but it's
something we're going to learn next.
But it all comes from, it suggests
one thing, is that there's
quantization, meaning that we
have specific energy levels.
So we have n is equal to
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, to infinity.
Now, every single one of these, when we
have an excited level, when we promote
an electron to a higher level, it goes
from a ground state, so its lowest
level, so wherever it's relaxed, to a
newer, higher state, right, whenever
that happens, so when it's excited.
Now, we label all these with quantum
numbers, which is really useful, right,
so all of the rows on your periodic
table are going to be your quantum
numbers that we're going to see, so, and
it goes from 1 to 7, to make it really
easy for us for our first semester, and.
As you get farther in chemistry, you'll
find out it's more complicated than that.
Um, when it relaxes back down, this is
going to release energy and it's going to
be in the form of a photon that's going
to be observed, right, when this happens.
So you can either absorb a photon or
it can release one through relaxation.
And these transitions equal to
a very specific amount of energy
that can be calculated too, right?
You can calculate these different levels.
Um, if you were to try and do this using
those formulas I showed earlier, right?
So, energy is equal to h times, uh,
nu, or you can also use, uh, energy
being related to, um, h times the speed
of light divided by the wavelength.
So you can use that as
well to find energy.
Um, this is what essentially tells
you that every element has its own
characteristic spectrum, telling
you that every element is different
and lets you see how the subatomic
particles exist and they all behave
differently, which is the cool part.
Okay, so that is enough for this video.
I've talked for a while.
I'm sorry.
I hope that this helped a little bit
to try to understand the quantum, which
for the physics people out there, if
there are a few of you, And I hope
that it kind of showed you what you
will see when you get to physics 4C.
Um, and also for the people
that are in general chem, that's
through Gen Chem 1A and 1B.
This is further, you'll get
going further later too.
And if you're not and you're just
health science and bio, just keep
in mind it gets crazy and gets